Discover the adventure behind the greatest mystery of our time.
Anastasia is a animation, family, fantasy film directed by Don Bluth.
Ten years after she was separated from her family, an eighteen-year-old orphan with vague
memories of the past sets out to Paris in hopes of reuniting with her grandmother.
She is accompanied by two con men, who intend to pass her off as the
Grand Duchess Anastasia to the Dowager Empress for a reward.
Anastasia (voice), played by Meg Ryan.
Dimitri (voice), played by John Cusack.
Vladimir (voice), played by Kelsey Grammer.
Rasputin (voice), played by Christopher Lloyd.
Bartok (voice), played by Hank Azaria.
Sophie (voice), played by Bernadette Peters.
Anastasia is a 1997 American animated musical historical fantasy film directed and produced by Don Bluth and Gary Goldman from a screenplay by the
writing teams of Susan Gauthier and Bruce Graham, and Bob Tzudiker and Noni White, and based on a story adaptation by Eric Tuchman.
It features songs written by Stephen Flaherty and Lynn Ahrens and a
musical score composed and conducted by David Newman.
The film stars the voices of Meg Ryan, John Cusack, Kelsey Grammer, Christopher Lloyd,
Hank Azaria, Bernadette Peters, Kirsten Dunst, and Angela Lansbury.
Set in an alternate 1926, it follows an amnesiac Anastasia
Romanov who embarks on a journey to discover her past.
Anastasia was the first 20th Century Fox animated feature to be produced by its own animation
division, 20th Century Fox Animation, through its subsidiary Fox Animation Studios.
The film premiered at the Ziegfeld Theater in New York City on November 14,
1997, and was released in the United States on November 21.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, who praised the animation, voice performances, and soundtrack,
though it attracted criticism from some historians for its fantastical retelling of the Grand Duchess.
Anastasia grossed $140 million worldwide, making it the most
profitable film from Bluth and Fox Animation Studios.
It received nominations for several awards, including for Best Original Song ("Journey to the
Past") and Best Original Musical or Comedy Score at the 70th Academy Awards.
The success of Anastasia spawned a franchise, including a direct-to-video
spin-off in 1999 and a stage musical adaptation in 2016.
The film explores themes of nightmare, villain, czar /
tsar / tzar, musical, based on true story.